A Guide to the Leesburg Garden Club Collection, 1920-
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Leesburg Garden Club Collection 1920-2010
Thomas Balch Library
M 044
The collection contains records of the Leesburg Garden Club and includes directories, histories, minutes, committee reports, annual reports, scrapbooks, GCV information, information on the Leesburg Garden Club's participation in Garden Week in Virginia, photographs, information on the club's part in the adoption of zoning and a sign ordinance in Loudoun County, membership lists and information on the club's 501c3 status and other miscellaneous material.
Leesburg Garden Club, Loudoun County, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Leesburg Garden Club, Loudoun County, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2006.0200, 2010.0101
Historical Information
The Leesburg Garden Club was founded 9 December 1915 by four women, Mrs. Page (Bessie H.M.) Laughlin (1876-1950), Mrs. John (Frances P.) Gibson(1882-1964), Mrs. J.R.H. (Cora L.) Alexander (1884-1972), and Mrs. William (Norita F.) Martin (1876-1952). Early in 1916 eight additional women were invited to join, and by the end of 1917 there was a total of 22 members. By 2010 membership was limited to 40 active members, 15 associate members (members who for reasons acceptable to the Executive Board can no longer be active but who are entitled to the privileges of the club including voting), one non-resident member and such honorary members as the club and the Executive Board vote to include. Honorary members are people who have benefitted the club to a considerable extent. For example, the husband of a member was made an honorary member because of his work growing and hybridizing lilies which the club entered in many shows and with which it won many ribbons.
The club began as a group who met to read aloud from the works of Charles Dickens (1812-1870). One member mentioned hearing of something called a "garden club" and so Dickens was abandoned in favor of plants. Although named the Leesburg Garden Club, members came from all sections of Loudoun County and in the beginning many of them lived on farms as well as in the Town of Leesburg. Almost all had vegetable gardens, so there was initially as much emphasis on vegetables as on flowers.
On 18 May, 1926 the Leesburg Garden Club became the 14th member of the Garden Club of Virginia (GCV) which had been founded in 1920 with the object of encouraging preservation, conservation, beautification, and restoration in the state. The GCV organized Garden Week in Virginia to earn money for this purpose and in 1929 the Leesburg Garden Club opened two historic houses and made "about $16." Proceeds have increased tremendously and by 2010 the club's gross receipts surpassed $10,000 for Garden Week, which takes place at the end of April each year.
From the beginning the club had a number of civic projects as well as the members' own interests in gardening. Starting in 1917 members supplied fresh vegetables to the local hospital from their own gardens and from a garden which they established on the hospital grounds. They canned produce to provide vegetables for the staff and patients in winter in the days before freezers. This program continued until the early 1940s when the club switched its attention to landscaping at the hospital. Members also planted flowers to cheer up patients. Another early project was to help elementary school children plant flowers and teach them about beautification. This project expanded to become the Highway Development Committee and eventually the Beautification Committee which promotes the aesthetic improvement of Loudoun County and its towns and highways.
The club's concern with county beautification led it to work actively in opposition to the use of billboards. One member, Vinton Liddell Pickens (1900-1993), particularly urged the use of zoning to prevent the construction of billboards. She regularly attended meetings of the Board of Supervisors until the board agreed to appoint a Planning Commission to write a zoning ordinance. Vinton Pickens was the commission's first and longest serving chairman. Through the work of the Leesburg Garden Club, in 1942 Loudoun County became the first rural county in the country to have a zoning ordinance.
In 1985 the club became embroiled in a conflict with Lyndon LaRouche (1922 - ), an extremist political figure. LaRouche moved his headquarters to Loudoun County, and one of his organizations, Campaign Publications, Inc., filed for a variance to change the use of its agriculturally zoned property. The Leesburg Garden Club joined other concerned groups and citizens to protest the request. The Board of Zoning Appeals denied the request in February of 1986, and LaRouche and his supporters targeted those who opposed the variance with media attacks. Leesburg Garden Club members were described by LaRouche in an interview as "these clacking busybodies in this Soviet jellyfish front sitting here in Leesburg oozing out their funny little propaganda making nuisances of themselves."
The Leesburg Garden Club became a non-profit 501c3 organization in 1999 and has continued its civic work in order to maintain that status. The club has worked with Oatlands Plantation and Dodona Manor in preserving and maintaining these historic properties, which are open to the public. Each year it sends a child to Nature Camp where he or she learns the value and interest of nature conservation. A college scholarship is awarded each year to a high school student who will be studying in a horticulture related field. A long established custom has been for the members to meet in December to create wreaths and decorative greens to hang on Leesburg's unique swinging courthouse yard gates and the doors of Thomas Balch Library, the town's history and genealogy library. Other projects undertaken in the past have included encouraging homeowners to beautify their yards by giving them daffodil bulbs, planting dogwood trees in public spaces, and persuading the town of Leesburg to place hanging baskets of flowers on utility poles. The club monitors the county's sign ordinance and works with the county when amendments are necessary; this has happened only twice in the 70 years since it was adopted as part of the zoning ordinance.
The club also is active in gardening activities such as horticulture, flower arranging and flower shows. It takes part in the major GCV shows as well as sponsoring them when its turn comes in the GCV rotation. Members have won statewide awards for their work in conservation, preservation and beautification including, the GCV Massie Medal four times for saving the Broad Run bridge, introducing zoning to the county, for horticultural achievement and for donating trees for the Douglass Community Center "Park for all Ages." The club won the GCV Common Wealth Award for that park, and a member won the GCV deLacy Grey Memorial Medal for her work to protect the natural resources of the commonwealth. 10 members have won the GCV Horticultural Award of Merit.
Scope and Content
The collection contains records of the Leesburg Garden Club and includes directories, histories, minutes, committee reports, annual reports, scrapbooks, GCV information, information on the Leesburg Garden Club's participation in Garden Week in Virginia, photographs, information on the club's part in the adoption of zoning and a sign ordinance in Loudoun County, membership lists and information on the club's 501c3 status and other miscellaneous material.
Early records of the club were lost when the historian died. Consequently, most of the material begins with the1940s although there are a few earlier items including histories and some meeting/yearbooks. Minutes from 1995 and 2007 are also missing. This is an open collection and additional material will be added at least every two years.
The collection includes seven scrapbooks dating from 1948 through part of 2008. The material which would have been placed in a scrapbook during and after 2008 is currently being put into folders for better preservation. Much of the material, especially in the early books, is in very fragile condition. Material which had come loose from pages has been placed in containers with interleaved notations of where those missing pages may be found. Some Garden Week material and yearbooks may also be found in the scrapbooks.
Files on Historic Garden Week note many addresses and locations of houses which may be compared with the Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County, 1971-1983 (M 022), Architectural Surveys of Leesburg, 1971-2001(M 016), and Loudoun County Architectural Surveys, Supplement, 2003 (M 011) for more information on many of the buildings.
Arrangement
Box folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, U.S. Census, Social Security Death Index, www.ancestrylibrary.com (Accessed 19 July 2011).
Blue Ridge Herald, obituary, 21 July 1932.
Blue Ridge Herald, obituary, 26 October 1950.
"A Brief Biography of Lyndon H. LaRouche, Jr.," http://www.larouchepub.com/resume.html (Accessed 21 July 2011).
Find a Grave, www.findagrave.com (Accessed 19 July 2011).
Leesburg Garden Club Collection, 1920 - (M 044), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Loudoun Times Mirror, obituary, 30 July 1964.
The Washington Post, obituary, 13 August 2003.
The Garden Club of Virginia, Follow the Green Arrow: The History of the Garden Club of Virginia, 1920-1970: Richmond: The Dietz Press, 1970.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Lewis/Edwards Architectural Surveys of Loudoun County, Virginia, 1971-1983 (M O22); Loudoun County Architectural Surveys Supplement, 2003 (M 011); Leesburg Architectural Surveys, 1971-2001 (M 016), Lyndon LaRouche Collection, 1979-1986 (SC0075), Follow the Green Arrow: The History of the Garden Club of Virginia, 1920-1970, Mrs. James Bland Martin, V REF 635.9 MAR
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - List of Members, 1966-1967
  - List of Members, 1970-1971, 1971-1971, 1972-1973
  - Membership Lists, 1993, 1994, 1995
  - Membership List, 1995
  - Attendance Records, 1974-1985
  - Attendance Records, 1985-1986, 1986-1987, 1987-1988, 1988-1990, 1991-1992
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1956, 1957
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1959, 1960
  - Executive Committee (Board) Minutes, 1964
  - Executive Committee (Board) Minutes, 1965
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1966, 1967, 1968
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1970-1971, 1972
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1973, 1974, 1975
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1976, 1977, 1978
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1986, 1987, 1988
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1989, 1990
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1991, 1992, 1993
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1994
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1995
  - Executive Board Minutes (wayside stand signage discussion), 1996
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1997
  - Executive Board Minutes (discussion of non-profit status), 1998
  - Membership Profiles (incomplete), 1981
  - Minutes (August & September only), 1955
  - Minutes, 1956
  - Minutes, 1957
  - Minutes (missing March and July), 1958
  - Minutes (GCV Rose Show; interstate billboard bill), 1959
  - Minutes 1960
  - Minutes (continuation billboard bill discussion) 1961
  - Minutes (missing January and October; GCV Daffodil Show), 1962
  - Minutes (missing June; Riverbend Dam threat), 1963
  - Minutes (Riverbend Dam; Massie Medal citation), 1964
  - Minutes (missing April), 1965
  - Minutes, 1966
  - Minutes (January-September; November; includes preparation for Board of Governors' meeting of GCV), 1967
  - Minutes (January-March), 1968
- (Box 2)
  - Minutes (July-November), 1970
  - Minutes, 1971
  - Minutes (March-November), 1972
  - Minutes (missing January) (includes removal of last billboard), 1973
  - Minutes (January-August, October, November), 1974
  - Minutes (missing January, February, May incomplete, August, September), 1975
  - Minutes (see November membership system proposed change), 1976
  - Minutes, 1977
  - Minutes (missing October) (membership system discontinued), 1978
  - Minutes, 1979
  - Minutes (GCV of Virginia lily show), 1980
  - Minutes, 1981
  - Minutes (2 sets & summaries April-November) (Common Wealth Award won by club), 1982
  - Minutes (2 sets), 1983
  - Minutes (missing November; some duplicates & summaries), 1984
  - Minutes (2 sets) (William Fitzhugh Rust (1916 - 1991) land donation to Leesburg for park; A.V. Symington (1916 - 2003), 1985
  - Minutes (2 sets), 1986
  - Minutes (2 sets), 1987
  - Minutes (3 sets), 1988
  - Minutes (3 sets), 1989
  - Minutes (none for October owing to GCV Board of Governors meeting in Leesburg) (2 copies January & February), 1990
- (Box 3)
  - Secretary's information, 2003
  - Minutes (missing January, July, August, October), 1991
  - Minutes (missing January), 1992
  - Minutes (missing May), 1993
  - Minutes (missing May), 1994
  - Minutes (missing January, May), 1996
  - Minutes (missing May), 1997
  - Minutes (missing April, June, September) (some Treasurer's reports; incorporation of club - 501c3 status), 1998
  - Minutes (missing June, September-October), 1999
  - Minutes (includes membership list), 2000
  - Minutes (includes membership list), 2001
  - Minutes (includes membership list; GCV Daffodil Show in Leesburg), 2002
  - Minutes (GCV Daffodil Show 2nd year in Leesburg), 2003
  - Minutes, 2004
  - Minutes, 2005
  - Minutes, 2006
  - Minutes (July, August, September only), 2008
  - Minutes (includes Treasurer's reports), 2009
  - Christmas raffle, 1994
- (Box 4)
  - Executive Board: method of voting for new members
  - Executive Board re: reopening a meeting, what to do if a nominee declines, 2009
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1999-2006, 2009
  - Executive Board Minutes, 2010
  - Membership minutes, 2008
  - Membership minutes, 2009
  - Membership minutes, 2010
  - Membership minutes, 2011
- (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook: loose at front of scrapbook change to by-laws 1948, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 1 (President's Report 1948, handbook 1947), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 4 (handbook 1951), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 8 (report of GCV annual meeting of 1948), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 9, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 10, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 12, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 14, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 18, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 19, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 20, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 21, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 23, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 24, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 40 (herb garden), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 45 (trees & shrubs noted by George Washington, GCV Lily Show 1949), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 54 (Garden Week 1951), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 61, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 64 (Garden Week 1951), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 87 (dogwood planting), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 96 (garden week page 2 of article in book), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 104 (lily chairman report 1952), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 106, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 124 ("Fabulous Facts of Nature"), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 132 (Burr Powell Harrison (1911 - 2000) garden, Leesburg), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 144, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 152 ("Fall in the Garden"), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 158 (Rose Show photograph), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 162 (p. 2 of "Poisonous Plants"), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 166, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 167, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 172 (proposed officers & amendments to by-laws), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 174, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: pages 175, 176, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 177, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 178 (rose care), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 179 (old roses), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 180 (chrysanthemums), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 181, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 182, 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 183 (Garden Week 1955), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: from back of book (special mid-term election of president), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: loose at back of book (GCV Daffodil Show 1954), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: loose at back of book (City of Fairfax dam on Goose Creek), 1948-1955
  - Scrapbook: page 14 (Garden Week 1956), 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 22 Gibson garden, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 34 Oak Hill, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 35 Locust Hill, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 37 Rockland, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 46 (end of book) Ellwood, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: page 46 (end of book) Oatlands, 1954-1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 1, 1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 2, 1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 4, 1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 5, 1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 15, 1959
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 1959: page 21, 1959
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book (plant sale 1976, 1981), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: front of book (Garden Week 1977), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: front of book (Garden Week 1976), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book (Garden Week brochures 1983), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 3, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 10, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 10, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 10 (photographs of various projects), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 10 (photographs of decorating for Christmas), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 14 (preparing for plant sale - photographs), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 14 (Common Wealth award), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 16 (flower show 1945), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 48 (Loudoun Times Mirror garden section 4/19/79), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: page 75 (garden week 1983), 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book, 1975-1983
  - Scrapbook: loose in front of book, 1983-1987
  - Scrapbook: loose at page 5 (garden week 1985), 1983-1987
  - Scrapbook: page 13 (photographs of Board of Governors' meeting 1985), 1983-1987
  - Scrapbook: loose at page 28, 1983-1987
  - Scrapbook: page 33 (page 1 of 1983 report of historian), 1983-1987
- (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook: page 11 (sign ordinance revisions - wayside stands), 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: pages 12 & 13 ("A Floral Menu" - recipes using edible flowers), 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: pages 14-17 (photographs of edible flowers), 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: page 18, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: sign ordinance indictments 1997, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: pages 20, 21, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Joan Stafford-Allen Williams (1907-2003): article, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Oatlands greenhouse: article, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: article re weddings of three former presidents, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: see folder 9, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens for Town of Leesburg in 1995, photographs, page 1, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs 1995, page 2, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 3, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 4, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 5, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 6, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 7, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 8, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: Making Christmas greens, photographs, 1995, page 9, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: flower show at Virginia Museum of Fine Arts 2007, 1995-1997
  - Scrapbook: article, Betty Whiting Flemming's (1926 - 2009) death, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: Garden Week 2008, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: Garden Club of Virginia daffodil show 2008, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: illegal signs, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: Betty Flemming's funeral, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: scholarship, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: article "The Modern Garden Club," 21 July 2010, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: GCV Rose Show photographs, 2010, 2008-2010
  - Scrapbook: article, beginning of sign ordinance and zoning, 2008-2010
- (Box 7)
  - Receipts for Garden Week, 1929
  - Houses open for Garden Week by year & by address/location
  - Restored gardens financed by Garden Week in Virginia
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1950, 1953, 1956
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1957, 1958, 1959
  - Garden Week, publicity (Rockland, Belgrove), 1959
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, Garden Week fact sheet, 1960, 1961, 1962
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1963, 1965, 1966
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1967
  - Garden Week publicity, Oak Hill, Little Oatlands, Woodburn, Cox, Williams, Isaacs, & Crabites houses in Leesburg, 1967
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1968
  - Garden Week information, Little Oatlands, Oatlands, Oak Hill, Rockland, Oatlands Hamlet, Noland House, Morven Park, 1969
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1969
  - Garden Week, brochure & ticket, 1969
  - Garden Week, publicity, Oak Hill, Oatlands, Little Oatlands, Oatlands Hamlet, Noland House, Morven Park, Rockland, 1969
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1970, 1971, 1972
  - Garden Week brochure, 1971
  - Garden Week publicity, Woodburn, Oatlands, Little Oatlands, Oatlands Hamlet, Oak Hill, Metzger House (in Leesburg), Chatel House (in Leesburg), Morven Park, 1971
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1973
  - Garden Week general information, 1973
  - Garden Week, brochures (3 copies), 1973
  - Garden Week publicity, Limestone Quarter, Morven Park, Eckles Estate, Hedgeland, Oak Hill, Oatlands, Fletcher garden (in Leesburg), Mills House (in Leesburg), 1973
  - Garden Week ticket, 1973
  - Garden Week, Highway Department-signs
  - Garden Week, invitations and bus tours, 1973
  - Garden Week, advertising information, 1973
  - Garden Week, hostess information, 1973
  - Garden Week, financial information, 1973
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1974
  - Garden Week in Virginia, brochures (Middleburg area) (two copies), 1974
- (Box 8)
  - Garden Week 1975, publicity (1 of 4): Little Oatlands, Oatlands Hamlet, Oak Hill, Harrison-Trone House (later called Glenfiddich, originally Harrison Hall) in Leesburg, Sage Hill, Cox House in Leesburg, 1975
  - Garden Week, publicity (2 of 4): Dietz house at 11 Cornwall St. N.W., 1975
  - Garden Week, publicity (3 of 4), 1975
  - Garden Week, publicity (4 of 4), 1975
  - Garden Week, descriptions of houses, 1975
  - Garden Week, brochure, copy for printer, 1975
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" book, 1975
  - Garden Week, summary, 1975
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia," book, 1977
  - Garden Week, publicity, correspondence, 1977
  - Garden Week, brochure, 1977
  - Garden Week, publicity, printed articles with photographs, 1977
  - Garden Week, publicity, house descriptions: Little Spring, Oak Hill, Oatlands Hamlet, Little Oatlands, Braddock and Trowbridge houses (both in Leesburg), 1977
  - Garden Week (Middleburg area, sponsored by Fauquier-Loudoun Garden Club with help from Leesburg Garden Club), brochure, 1978
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia," booklet, 1979
  - Garden Week, brochure: Braddock House (In Leesburg), 19 (old street number) West (now northwest) Loudoun St. in Leesburg, 11 West (now northwest) Cornwall St. in Leesburg, Belgrove, Burr Ridge, Oatlands Hamlet, Little Oatlands, Oak Hill, 1979
  - Garden Week, publicity and house descriptions, 1979
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" booklet, 1980
  - "Historic Garden Week in Virginia" booklet, 1981
  - Garden Week, ticket, brochures (3 copies): (addresses are old street numbers) Shea house 49 (old street number) West (now northwest) Cornwall St., Conrad house 20 West (now northwest) North St., Rokeby, Oatlands Hamlet, Little Oatlands, Church of our Saviour, Oatlands miller's house, Oat Hill, 1981
  - Garden Week, publicity and house descriptions, 1981